Guide to the John T. Jones, Jr. Business and Personal Papers MS 725
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
John T. Jones, Jr. Business and Personal Papers
1950-2000
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Houston Endowment, Inc.
MS 725
14.75 Linear Feet 23 boxes
John T. Jones, Jr. papers document his business dealings through his business and non-profit interests, and public appearances, as well as his personal and family life. Included are correspondence, newsclips, military records, income tax and insurance records, photographs and speeches.
Biographical Note
Son of Margaret and John T. Jones, Sr. and nephew of Jesse H. Jones, John T. Jones, Jr. was born in Dallas, TX on Dec. 2, 1917. The family moved to Houston where Jones attend public schools at Montrose Elementary, Lanier Junior High and graduated from San Jacinto High School in 1935. He then attended New Mexico Military Institute and graduated in 1938 with a commission as 2nd Lieutenant in the U.S. Army Reserve. In fall 1938, Jones entered the University of Texas to major in business and journalism. From June through August 1939 he toured Western Europe with letters of introduction from Jesse H. Jones.
Before graduating from the University of Texas, Jones was called to activie duty by the Army. He trained in Kentucky, North Carolina and Louisiana before shipping out to England and Ireland. During duty in Tunisia, Jones and his unit were captured by the Germans. Considered MIA/POW, Jones was transported to a prisoner of war camp, Oflag 64, in Szubin, Poland in June 1943 and remained there until 1945 when Germans force-marched prisoners deeper into Germany to flee Russians entering Poland. Jones returned to Houston following D-Day, and in Oct. 1945 married Winifred Small.
Jones went to work for the Houston Chronicle, owned by his uncle Jesse H. Jones. He gradually assumed greater responsibilities for Jesse Jones Interests and upon Jesse's death assumed full stewardship, which included Houston Endowment, Inc. He resigned his position as president of Houston Endowment in 1965 and served as president of Houston Chronicle from 1950 until 1966 from which he resigned to pursue oversight of KTRH Radio and KTRK Television as president of the Rusk Corporation. As a major Houston philanthropist, Jones gave time and energy to many local and national organizations, including National Conference of Chirstians and Jews, United Negro College Fund, Variety Boys Club, Society for the Performing Arts and Jesse H. Jones Hall for the Performing ARts. Jones continued his business and community activities in Houston until his death in 1994.
Scope and Contents
John T. Jones, Jr. papers document his business dealings through his business and non-profit interests, and public appearances, as well as his personal and family life. Included are correspondence, newsclips, military records, income tax and insurance records, photographs and speeches.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers were donated by Houston Endowment, Inc., Dec. 2017.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in seven series as follows: Series I: Business Interests Series II: Non-profit activities Series III: Public appearances Series IV: Correspondence Series V: Personal and family Series VI: Photographs Series VII: Oversize
Related Materials
See also Jesse H. Jones Corporate and Property Records 1836-2008, MS621; and Jesse H. Jones Personal and Family Papers 1841-2000, MS252.
Index Terms
Subjects
Business; Soldiers -- Correspondence; World War (1939-1945); Newspapers; Prisoners of war; Insurance; Military
Document Types
personal correspondence; photographs; tax records
Places
Texas--Houston
Subjects (Persons)
Jones, John T., Jr., 1917-1994; Jones, Jesse H. (Jesse Holman)
Subjects (Corporations)
Houston Endowment, Inc.
- Series I: Business interests
  - Sub-series A: Houston Chronicle
    - Dept. of Justice, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hurricane Carla [see also oversize box 23], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Newspaper Publishers Association, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Associated Press, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ft. Worth Star-Telegram, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Washington bureau, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Media contacts (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - John Emmerich, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Jess Gibson, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - RIchard J.V. Johnson, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ray Powers, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - W.P. Steven, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - M.E. Walter, 1959, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - F.E. Warren (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Purchase of Houston Press, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Sale of Houston Chronicle, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Resignation of John T. Jones, Jr., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - General interest (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sub-series B: Jesse H. Jones Interests
    - American General Insurance Co., 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American General Insurance Co., Maryland Casualty Co. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ft. Worth properties, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Houston banks, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Houston Consolidated Television, 1954-1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Jesse H. Jones Interests, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Jesse H. Jones interests, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Jesse H. Jones interests, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - KTRH Broadcasting Co., 1930-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mayfair House, New York, NY, 1955-1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mayfair House, New York, NY, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Mayfair House, New York, NY, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - National Bank of Commerce, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - National Bank of Commerce Houston and Texas National Bank Houston merger, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 14, Box 3, Folder 1-5)
    - Reagan State Bank of Houston, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Reconstruction Finance Corp. book, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Rice Hotel, Houston, TX, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Settegast estate, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sub-series C: John T. Jones, Jr.
    - CRS Design Associates, 1976-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Frontier Energy, 1982-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Rusk Corp., 1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Windsor Properties, 1988-1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sub-series D: Press coverage
    - Business Week, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Newsweek, 1962-06-11 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Marathon World, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series II: Non-profit activities
  - Alley Theater, Houston, TX, 1964-1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Association for Community Television, Houston, TX, 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Baylor Medical Foundation, Houston, TX, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - B'nai B'rith, Washington, DC, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Cancer Congress, 10th International, Houston, TX, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Chamber of Commerce of Houston, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Chamber of Commerce, Huntsville and Waller Co., 1952 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Council for Financial Aid to Education, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Highway 290 Association, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Houston Endowment, Inc., 1951-1988 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Memorial Oaks Presbyterian Church, Houston, TX, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Museum of Medical Science, Houston, TX, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - National Jewish Hospital, Denver, CO, 1964, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - National Space Hall of Fame, Washington, DC, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Radio Free Europe, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - San Jacinto Museum of History, Texas, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Society for the Performing Arts, Houston, TX, 1967-1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Texas Bill of Rights Foundation, Houston, TX, 1967-1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Texas Heritage Foundation, Austin, TX, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Texas Medical Center Library, Houston, TX [see also oversize box 23], 1947-1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Texas Women's University, Denton, TX, 1961-1964 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - United Negro College Fund, Houston, TX, 1958-1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - University of Texas, Austin, TX, 1961-1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Variety Boys Club, Houston, TX, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - YMCA Development Program, Houston, TX, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Committee participants, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Federal and state challenges to private foundations, 1961-1985 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Series III: Public appearances
  - Sub-series A: Events
    - American Society of Newspaper Editors party, Washington, DC, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Inauguration of President of Mexico, Mexico City, Mexico, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - National Governors Conference, Houston, TX, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Stitzel-Weller Distillery party, Louisville, KY, 1965-01-21 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - White House dinner, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - White House luncheon for Texas newspaper editors, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series B: Speeches
    - 1948-1949 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1952 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1953 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1954 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1955 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1956 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1960 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1964 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1965 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1968 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - 1977 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - not dated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - source materials (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Correspondence
  - Sub-series A: Business/personal
    - 1945-1947 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1949 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - 1950 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 1951 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - 1952 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - 1953 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1954 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1955 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1956 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - on death of Jesse H. Jones, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 5-9, Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1957 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1958 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1959 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1960 Jan-June (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1960 July-Dec (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1961 Jan-June (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1961 July-Dec (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1962 Jan-Aug (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1962 Sept-Oct (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1962 Nov-Dec (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1963 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - re: Charles Novosad, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - re: Henderson Shuffler, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - 1964 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1965 Jan-June (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1965 July-Dec (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 1966 Jan-July (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 1966 Aug-Dec (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 1967 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - 1968 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - 1969 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1970 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1971 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 1972 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1973 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1974 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1975 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - 1976 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - 1977 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - 1993 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Sub-series B: Family
    - John T. Jones, Sr. and Jesse H. Jones, 1933-1944 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Mary Gibbs Jones and Margaret Jones, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Sub-series C: European tour
    - John T. Jones, Jr. to parents, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - John T. Jones, Jr. and Jessie Bailey (sister), 1939 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Letter of introduction, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Memorabilia, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Sub-series D: World War II
    - to family, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - to family, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - to family, 1942-1944 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - to family, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - to family, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - to Bill and Jessie Bailey, 1941-1944 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - to family, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Honeymoon, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - to Emma Jones Bobo, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Jesse H. Jones to John T. Jones, Jr., 1941 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - from friends, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Mrs. John T. Jones, Sr. from James Bobo, 1943-1945 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - to John T. Jones, Sr. (on son's MIA/POW status), 1943 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - to Mrs. John T. Jones, Sr. (on son's MIA/POW status), 1943 (Box 14, Folder 12-13)
    - to M/M John T. Jones, Sr. (on son's MIA/POW status), 1943 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - to John T. Jones, Jr. from mother (letters unopened), 1943-01-1943-03 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Family on arrangements for John T. Jones, Jr., 1943-1945 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - to John T. Jones, Jr. (POW) from Mrs. John T. Jones, Sr., 1944 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Series V: Personal and family
  - Sub-series A: Schooling
    - Elementary school, 1928-1929 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - San Jacinto Senior High School, 1935 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Research papers, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - New Mexico Military Institute, 1938-1944 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - College class notes, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - College letters and photographs, 1939-1940 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - College fraternities, 1940-1966 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Texas Exes Association, 1956-1982 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Sub-series B: Military service
    - Records, 1936-1940 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Records, 1941-1945 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Records, 1946-1953 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - "The Newswheel", 1943 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript "War is Hell..." by L. Robertson, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript "Tank Soldiers Journal", 1989 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Newsclips, 1978-1993 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Photograph: with mother on return from war, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Project POW, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - POW correspondence, 1994 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Texas POW Club, 1948-1987 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - OFLAG 64 POW reunions, 1963, 1964, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - OFLAG 64 POW reunion, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Artifacts (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Sub-series C: Clubs
    - Allegro, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Bayou, 1966-1991 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Houston, 1968-1982 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Lakeside Country Club, 1964-1966 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Paul Jones Dancing, 1986-1992 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Petroleum, 1964-1970 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Philosophical Society of Texas, 1955-1962 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Quail Creek Country Club, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Tejas, 1954-1982 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series D: Travel
    - Family vacation, 1961 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Family vacation, 1967 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Sub-series E:
    - John T. Jones, Jr.
      - Passport (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Passes to U.S. House of Representatives, Washington, DC, 1937 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Address books (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Death, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Winifred Small Jones
      - Biographical (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1939-1945 (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - Texas Women's University, 1959-1967 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges, 1964-1965 (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - Address book (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Insurance
      - American General Life, 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - American General Home, 1948-1958 (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - American General Property and Personal Liability, 1947-1957 (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - C&I Life, 1948-1951 (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - Great Southern Life, 1928-1929 (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - John Hancock Life, 1942-1946 (Box 18, Folder 19)
      - National Service Life, 1943-1946 (Box 18, Folder 20)
      - Dallas Title and Guaranty Co., 1946 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - Banking
      - Leases (Box 18, Folder 22)
      - Stocks (Box 18, Folder 23)
      - Power of Attorney (Box 18, Folder 24)
      - Interest (Box 18, Folder 25)
      - Real estate (Box 18, Folder 26)
    - Income tax (John T. Jones, Jr. and Winifred Small Jones)
      - 1938-1947 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - 1948-1951 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - 1960 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Newsclips
      - POW (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Family, 1953-1994 (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Houston Chamber of Commerce, 1956-1958 (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Houston Chronicle (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - Houston Endowment, Inc., 1957-1963 (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - KTRK, 1965-1967 (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - Public service, 1964-1975 (Box 19, Folder 14)
      - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 15)
      - Desegregation, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 16)
      - [University of] Texas Exes, 1956-1960 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Jesse H. Jones and family (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - John T. Jones, Jr. youth (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - John T. Jones, Jr. adult (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - John T. Jones, Jr. with others [see also oversize box 23] (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Military: Northern Ireland, 1942 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Military: POW [see also oversize box 23], 1943-1945, 1978 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Winifred Small Jones (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - John T. and Winifred S. Jones (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Christmas (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Children (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - University of Texas fraternity, 1939 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Swamp, ca. 1950 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Farm (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Houston Chronicle [see also oversize box 23] (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Houston Chronicle service recognitions (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Houston City Council, 1962 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Public service (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - KTRK (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Allen Military Academy, dedication of Jesse Jones Hall, Bryan, TX, 1959-10-25 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - American Newspaper Publishers Association, NY, 1960 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Jesse H. Jones Hall for the Performing Arts dedication, Houston, TX, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, Houston, TX, 1957-03-12 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson reception for President of Mexico, LBJ ranch, 1959 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Galveston meeting (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Texas Friendship for Korea, Houston, TX, 1955 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Palm Beach party (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - [University of] Texas Exes, 1957 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Lindsey Blayney (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Omar Bradley (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Oveta Culp Hobby (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson, 1959 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - John F. Kennedy, 1963 (Box 22, Folder 13)
- Series VII: Oversize
  - Sub-series A: Photographs
    - Mary Gibbs Jones (2) (Box 23)
    - Jesse H. Jones (3) (Box 23)
    - POW reunion, Shamrock Hilton Hotel, Houston, TX, 1978-10 (Box 23)
    - John T. Jones, Jr. with others (Box 23)
    - Houston Chronicle warehouse (2), 1953 (Box 23)
  - Souvenir edition Houston Chronicle on Hurricane Carla, 1961-09-10 (Box 23)
  - Proposed Additions to the Jesse H. Jones Library Building in the Texas Medical Center, 1966 (Box 23)